All right, new Dolphins general manager
John Eric Soliv. Man, welcome in. Thanks
for your time today.
>> I appreciate you having me.
>> Not a bad setting for an interview,
right? Pretty cool digs. What's your
early impression so far of Miami and the
uh the work environment?
>> Better weather. We'll start there. Um a
lot of really good people. Uh a lot of
people extended a helping hand, make
sure that uh when I come through the
door, I have what I need. And um I can
tell there's a lot of people here that
are eager to to build a winner and and
kind of get this thing going and ready
to work hard. And we got a lot of work
ahead of us. There's no doubt about it.
But I think uh the process will take us
where we want to go. [music] But the
people that are involved in that process
are equally, if not more important, and
I can tell right from the bat we got a
really good culture and group of people
in place to help us get going.
>> Yeah, myself and Dolphins fans are
excited to hear more about that process.
We'll get to that here in just one
second. But what does it mean to you to
get this opportunity? First time GM.
What's what's the opportunity mean to
you?
>> It means everything. You know, I grew up
in this business. My dad's a longtime
NFL coach, right around the 30-year
mark. Um, I grew up around the the game.
Um, I think anytime [music] you get a
chance to put your fingerprints on
something and build something special
along with a lot of other really good
people, uh, that's a special
opportunity. I was raised in Green Bay
and in in my football career. Um, I
believe wholeheartedly in the process
that I'm bringing through the door and
quite frankly, I hope long after I'm
gone, that process is still in place
here, much like Ron Wolf brought it to
Green Bay and it's still in place there.
You know, I would say that's my hope,
you know, that we win a bunch of games
and when I take off from here that that
the fingerprints are still in place and
and they keep that going down the road
for for long-term sustained success.
>> So, I'm glad you mentioned Ron Wolf in
the process because Ron Wolf, Ted
Thompson, Guda, and yourself now here
with Miami Dolphins. You've spoken about
the opportunity to be a part of the
proven process over sustained time,
right? Building a sustained winner. How
would you summarize that process and
what are the key takeaways you have from
your time there that will carry forward
into this role? We're going to draft and
develop and retain our own. It's
important to us that we raise our own
because that's culture, right? We don't
want a team full of mercenaries. Um,
that creates problems on multiple
levels. But then within that, it's who
you infuse into that locker room. You
know, we want we want people who love
football, um, who want to be the best
that they can be, who are selfless, who
who are good teammates. And then we're
going to use every player or every
avenue of player acquisition to
supplement this roster. We'll be very
intentional and deliberate on how we go
about it in free agency because that can
be dangerous waters uh if you don't
handle it the right way. But that's how
we'll that's how we'll move. You know,
it'll be build through the draft, retain
our own, supplement uh and other avenues
of free uh free agency and practice
squad steals and all all that all that
goes with it waiverwires and build this
team out best we can. But at every
avenue, we will strengthen this roster.
given the opportunity.
>> You know, some teams around the league
have this like universally recognized
player prototype, right? Like if the
Dolphins develop that under your watch,
what do you want that to be? Like what
type of player do you want pundits to
look at a player and say that right
there, that's a Miami [music] Dolphin.
>> I think mental toughness, physical
toughness, you start there from from a
character standpoint. And again, a
burning desire to want to be the best
that you can be and win. That's what
we're all here to do at the end of the
day. If you broke it down to one word,
we're here to win. Um, and then within
that, you know, our our division runs
through Buffalo and New England and New
York, cold weather places. There's a
saying in our business, fast gets slow,
but big doesn't get small. So,
understand like we're not going to
sacrifice speed and explosion and skill
for a bunch of big, stiff guys. But we
are going to have substance to us at all
levels of our team. At corner, at
receiver, at running back, and certainly
up front, we will build this team.
starts with the quarterback and then we
will build this team from the inside
out. We got to be dominant on the
offensive line, dominant on the
defensive line, [music] and then
explosive and athletic on the perimeter
where we can attack all three levels of
the field and it gives that offensive
coordinator flexibility to call the game
the way that he wants to call the game
most importantly in any element.
>> Adaptable to what the opponent can show
you as well football. What's the process
in IDing a player that fits all that
criteria? I know it's a lot, but what's
the process of trying to find players
that fit that criteria?
>> It starts in the summer. you're watching
their junior sophomore tape depending on
what level of player he is. Um, so you
start there and then you go through your
college process in the fall of of going
to games, talking to a lot of different
people about the makeup of this play. I
always refer to it as football
character. What makes this guy tick?
Where does he come from in his personal
life? What experiences has he overcome?
What adversity has he overcome? And then
you you watch hours and hours and hours
full of of tape, you know, to to put a
value on this player. Um, and then
obviously you have the second part of
it, uh, with a lot more touch points,
all-star games, combine, uh, [music] pro
days, and the more information that
comes in, the clearer the picture gets.
Um, and then eventually, uh, you know,
we'll go through draft meetings. We'll
we'll have a lot of discussions with our
our scouts who have spent years at this
point identifying these players and
doing a lot of work on these players,
and [music] we'll set the board and uh,
and we'll go pick players that we think
number one will help this football team.
Look, at the end of the day, you got to
be able to play, right? You got to have
talent to come in here and make a
difference for this team. But then we
also want to make sure it's the right
kind of guy that we're infusing into
that locker room from a character
standpoint.
>> It's a long process. You got you have to
love it, right? You have to love it to
do this job effectively.
>> Yeah. I think if uh if you don't have a
passion for this game and for this job
in particular, um you'll drown because
it's a lot of work. It's a lot of late
nights. Uh it's not a nineto-five. And
if you're passionate about it, you
you'll do you'll do well at it. But if
you're not, um, you'll get identified
pretty quickly.
>> So, you've touched on this a few times
in this interview already, but during
the offseason, it can be so easy to get
caught up on the shiny object, right?
The big free agent sign that the early
draft pick, but I once heard you better
get your internal evaluations right.
Otherwise, you've got no shot. What's
the key to making that a reality?
Getting your internal evaluations mostly
right.
>> Yeah, I mean, you had Look, any good
scout knows their team better than they
know anything else. So, you know, we've
done the work there. Um there's a lot of
work to do on this team. Uh I've already
talked to some of the I've had a couple
of the guys pop up to my office and
we've talked about what's important to
them. We have 30 UFAS, you know, uh I
mean just start there. You can't bring
them all back. So there's going to be a
lot of work to do. Uh but we have some
nice pieces as well. Achain's a
differencemaker. Brewer is a really good
player. Brooks is a really good player
on defense. You know, there there are
building blocks and pieces. Patrick Paul
is a good left tackle. Um there's
pieces, but we have a lot of work to do
uh in certain areas. It's our job to
make sure that through the draft and
through the other avenues, we're making
this team as competitive as possible at
every position because competition
drives the individual to excellence. I
don't care if you're talking about on
the grid iron or if you're talking about
in the office place. If you don't have a
lot of weak links, everybody else is
going to get get better. And that that's
our job as a personnel staff and my job
as a general manager to make sure that
we're cultivating that day in and day
out with our football team and then what
goes on in that building.
>> My very next question was Han, Paul,
Brewer, Brooks, and Wadd. I add Wadd
You off top of your head so it makes
perfect sense. But I was going to ask
you, you know, because there's more
players than that obviously, but what
does excite you excite you most about
the young core talent you have here?
Because you mentioned speed and size,
all the things you want to find on the
football team. What about that core
really excites you the most? Hey, I
mean, I'll start with Jaylen. He's as
explosive um of an athlete. His ability
to create separation at the top route,
top of the route is as good as any. Um
obviously, Aane's production speaks for
itself. He's a three down back. He can
strike from anywhere on the field. Uh
he's a home run guy. Um Brewer's ability
to play out in space, snap, step, reach,
get to the second level. Uh and he plays
quite frankly [music] much bigger than
his listed size. Um, so, so I would say
we have a lot of explosion and
athleticism within the people that we
talked about there. And then Brooks is
just a ball player, man. He can run.
He's got great instincts. He'll strike
you. Um, that's an exciting group of
guys to build around. And then and then
Pat Paul is a huge man with with length
who, uh, plays a big man's game. Um, and
I talked to him the other day. I'm
really excited about him as we go
through the process of of building the
rest of that offensive line. I'm
laughing because Pat the person is just
he's so great. He's so great to get to
know and the way he plays in the field
is not at all how he is as a person.
It's it's a fun dichotomy there with
him. So year one will be different for
you here for the Dolphins and any other
year that you have here with Miami
because it's the first year where you
have to get to know your own roster. You
talk about watching film of Wadd and
those guys which I'm sure you did in
Green Bay for all 32 teams, right?
You're you're on top of all the rosters.
But how does that process work of
building out your free agency plan, your
draft board, and making sure all your
internal evaluations are buttoned up?
Yeah. So, we're, you know, our approach
within the draft is a best player
available approach. Um, you you really
have no idea what your needs are going
to be. And then as we build the board,
um, subconsciously
with a team value approach, you'll
[music] stack it for need, if that makes
sense. Okay. Um, and then within our
free agency process, that'll be much
more uh intentional about where we need
to fill gaps. I I believe in the free
agency process, you check you chase
difference makers.
>> I could talk philosophy with you all
day. I love this kind of stuff and I
want to get a little more broad here
talking about league cycles because
recently this is a league where you got
to get backers that can match up with
all the speed that offenses have. And
now we're seeing this return of the
power run element, right? And offenses
are trying to combat the speed on
defense by getting bigger. What are your
thoughts on the cyclical nature of
offensive football and where we're at in
terms of power run game, short high
percentage throws, playing shells, light
boxes, where we are in 2026 in the NFL?
>> Yeah, I think the best teams are the
ability or have the ability to be
multiple. That's the hardest to defend,
right? So again, when I talk about um
getting [music] big on the interior,
it's not necessarily at the sacrifice of
athleticism. We're not going to have
stiff guys that can't move because we
want to be multiple. We want to if there
are times in a game we want to get thick
on you and run more of a power gap
scheme. We have the ability to do that
and then there's times we want to run
off the ball, you know, and so, you
know, I guess that would be my answer to
that. I just I think the way that you
build this team um from a trait
standpoint, you have to be very
cognizant about being able to be
multiple so that you give that
coordinator on either side of the ball
the flexibility to call the game the way
that he wants you to call it. Um, I
don't think that, you know, it's a we
you have to affect the passer on
defense, right? But I think you have to
have two to three big men that when you
got to go stop the run, you have the
ability to do that. If you have a bunch
of sub guys that you're kicking down all
the time interiorly and you don't have
the ability to get big on you, they're
just going to run it down your throat.
So, you do, that's a great question,
number one, and it again, it's our job
and the personnel staff to make sure
that we're giving the coaches the
flexibility to be multiple on both sides
of the ball with our personnel. This is
a little bit redundant because you
talked about it a few times, but I I
watched a sit down you had for
Packers.com a couple years ago and you
talked about the draft is your
lifeblood. I mean, I just I love that
quote so much. We know that's obviously
true and you subscribed to that belief,
but maybe that's even more true today
than it was in years past. You think
that's the case? It's all I know. You
know what I mean? And I don't want to
come off as naive as if I don't
understand trends and efficiencies
around the league in terms of uh player
acquisition, but it's brought Green Bay
30 years of sustained success. It's what
I've been raised in for 22 years. I've
seen the fruits that it bears, you know.
Um I I just think it's the only way you
can go because again, um I think culture
is a huge deal, right? Culture is
everything. And when you draft and
develop and you raise your own, they're
bought in. They understand what the
standard is. When you fall into the trap
of bringing a bunch of guys in from all
over the place, um there is no standard.
Everybody's coming from a different
standard. And uh just again, I said it
earlier, a team full of mercenaries is a
scary place to be, you know, because
everybody's got a different agenda. When
you're raised in in one place together,
your agenda is the same, and that's to
go win ball games.
>> Well, you're coming into a program that
had a rookie class last year play 3,000
plus snaps in the season, and now you go
into a 2026 draft class with five picks
in the first three rounds. I know it's
very early on, but what's your thinking
of your approach here to this year's
draft, especially building upon a 2025
class that saw so much playing time for
the rookie class? It's probably not the
sexiest answer, but but the bottom line
is bring in good players that are wired
right for what we're trying to build.
That's it. I mean, obviously, I'm not
going to get any specifics on players
that we're looking at. And there's so
much more road to ho, if you will, uh,
in terms of the process, but yeah, I
mean, the simple answer is to make sure
we're bringing really good football
players in here that that are uh about
the right stuff.
>> One of my uh favorite publications, you
say, draft good players. That's the key
key to winning football. Uh from that
same interview, you talked about some of
the difficult conversations that have to
be had for scouting and decision-making.
I think the quote was if we're always
agreeing, we're not thinking. Uh how do
you foster an environment that promotes
that type of collaboration?
>> Yeah, I think uh a lot of the things we
talked about within my interview process
is [music] we all have a job to do.
Everybody's got a role in this thing and
they're all very important, equally
important. Um but it's collaboration
with boundaries and trust. I'm not going
to walk down to the head coach's door on
Saturday night and knock on his hotel
door and say, "Hey, look, here's a third
and long call sheet. we should run this.
It's not what I do. Um, at the end of
the day, everybody within my process,
everybody will have a seat at the table.
We'll be very deliberate and intentional
about how we go about that. Um, because
I want to make sure that we eliminate
the bias. Um, but at the end of the day,
everybody will have a say. The decision
making won't be collaborative because
you can't you're you're hiring me to
make decisions. If we start voting on
everything we do to make everybody feel
good, the value of the process is out
the window. So I think again making sure
the right people are part of the process
[music] is just as important as the
process itself. You got to eliminate the
pride, eliminate the ego. At the end of
the day, we all need to do what is best
for this place. You know, if I could
promise, and I'm not big on promises,
but if I could promise [music] anybody
one thing right now on camera, every
decision that is my responsibility, it
will never be about my personal agenda
or my relationships in the building.
It'll be about the Miami Dolphins and
what is best for this place. Period.
>> This is my favorite question the entire
interview. I'm a father of three. You're
a father of three. How excited is the
family to be down here in South Florida?
>> They're excited. They know there's a
beach and water. Um my older two are are
uh they're they're really excited. My
younger one was a Packer through and
through. So Cece, my nine-year-old, is
she's kind of like the little boy I have
never had. She plays flag football in an
all football all boy league and she was
a Packer through and through. So,
initially it was tough on her. She had
gotten to be buddies with a lot of the
players, but right before I left, she
drew me a pretty cool sketch of Waddle
and handed it to me and said, "Go to
work, Dad." So, I think we're heading in
the right direction.
>> I was going to say one one Wall of
Touchdown will take care of all that
she'll see it live and she'll be hooked
for the rest of her life. It's
>> coming around.
>> Perfect. New Dolphins general manager,
John Eric Sullivan, thanks for your time
today. Appreciate it.